Other useful mappings are,
还有另一些有用的映射
you might want to alias a command to itself
比如 你可能想给指令本身添加一个别名
but with a default flag.
但是带有缺省的参数
So here what is going on is I'm creating an alias
所以接下来 我要给 `mv` 创建一个别名
which is an alias for the move command,
用来代替它自己
which is MV and I'm aliasing it to the
same command but adding the "-i" flag.
它依然写作 mv 但多了一个参数 `-i`
And this "-i" flag, if you go through the man page
and look at it, it stands for "interactive".
查阅 man 手册可知 参数 `-i` 代表 interactive
And what it will do is it will prompt
me before I do an overwrite.
它会在覆盖文件之前弹出一个提示
So once I have executed this,
I can do something like
在我执行这个指令的时候，我可以做一些操作，比如
I want to move "aliases" into "case".
我想把 aliases 移动到 case
By default "move" won't ask, and if "case"
already exists, it will be over.
缺省状态下， 如果已经存在一个文件叫 case, mv 不会询问而是直接覆盖
That's fine, I'm going to overwrite
whatever that's there.
这没什么问题，我会把这个文件直接覆盖掉
But here it's now expanded,
但现在这个别名不只是 mv 了
"mv" has been expanded into this "mv -i"
mv 变成 mv -i 了
and it's using that to ask me
现在它提示我
"Oh, are you sure you want to overwrite this?"
哦 你真的要覆盖这个吗
And I can say no, I don't want to lose that file.
我如果不想失去原来的文件，就可以拒绝
Lastly, you can use "alias move"
最后 你可以执行 alias mv
to ask for what this alias stands for.
得知这一别名代表什么
So it will tell you so you can quickly make sure
你就可以很快确定
what the command that you
are executing actually is.
实际被执行的指令是什么
One inconvenient part about, for example,
having aliases is how will you go about
但这也有不便之处 比如
你该如何让别名
persisting them into your current environment?
在你的环境中始终有效
Like, if I were to close this terminal now,
比方说 如果我关掉这个终端
all these aliases will go away.
刚才设置的别名就会失效
And you don't want to be kind
of retyping these commands
你也不想一次又一次重新设置它们
and more generally, if you start configuring
your shell more and more,
往大了说，如果你开始折腾终端的配置
you want some way of bootstrapping
all this configuration.
就会希望所有配置能够自己加载好
You will find that most shell command programs
你会发现，大多数命令行软件
will use some sort of text
based configuration file.
都会使用某种文本配置文件
And this is what we usually call "dotfiles", because
they start with a dot for historical reasons.
它们通常被称为点文件
因为历史包袱让它们的文件名以点开头
So for bash in our case, which is a shell,
我们以 bash 这种 shell 为例
we can look at the bashrc.
它的配置文件在 .bashrc
For demonstration purposes,
here I have been using ZSH,
这是为了演示
我刚才一直在用 zsh
which is a different shell, and I'm going
to be configuring bash, and starting bash.
那是另一种 shell
我接下来要配置 bash 并且启动它
So if I create an entry here and I say
我可以在这里写一行
SL maps to LS
把 sl 映射到 ls
And I have modified that, and now I start bash.
改完了，然后启动 bash
Bash is kind of completely unconfigured,
but now if I do SL...
这里的 bash 没怎么被配置过
但是如果我执行 sl
Hm, that's unexpected.
emm... 怎么会这样呢
- You are not in your home directory.
- 这里不是家目录
Oh, good. Good getting that.
恩，是，说得好
So it matters where you config file is,
配置文件的位置很重要
your config file needs to be in your home folder.
你的配置文件在家目录才能生效
So your configuration file for
bash will live in that "~",
bash 的配置文件在 ~
which will expand to your home directory,
~ 会自动补全成你的家目录
and then bashrc.
然后是 .bashrc
And here we can create the alias
我们重新创建这个别名
and now we start a bash session and we do SL.
然后开一个 bash 执行 sl
Now it has been loaded, and this is
loaded at the beginning when this
现在就加载上了
这些配置会在 bash 启动时就被加载
bash program is started.
All this configuration is loaded and you can, not only use
aliases, they can have a lot of parts of configuration.
所有配置都加载好了
而你不仅可以配置别名，还有很多可以配置的选项
So for example here, I have a prompt
which is fairly useless.
比如说 我觉得这个提示符相当没用
It has just given me the name
of the shell, which is bash,
它只是告诉我这个 shell 的名字，显然是 bash
and the version, which is 5.0. I don't
want this to be displayed and
还有它的版本， 5.0
我不想看见这些信息
as with many things in your shell, this
is just an environment variable.
和 shell 中的许多东西一样，这就是个环境变量
So the "PS1" is just the prompt string
变量 PS1 就是 shell 的提示符
for your prompt and
并且
we can actually modify this
to just be a "> " symbol.
我们其实可以把它改成一个大于号
and now that has been modified, and we have
that. But if we exit and call bash again,
现在我们就改好了
可如果我们重启 bash 的话
that was lost. However, if we add this
entry and say, oh we want "PS1"
这个设置就丢失了
如果我们在 bashrc 里面添加 PS1 的配置
to be
把它改成
this and
这样
we call bash again, this has been persisted.
And we can keep modifying this configuration.
我们重启 bash 以后，设置依然有效
然后我们就可以继续修改配置
So maybe we want to include
或许我们想要把
where the
working directory that we are is in, and
当前的工作目录显示出来
that's telling us the same information
that we had in the other shell.
这就是我们在其他 shell 里面也会看到的信息
And there are many, many options,
此外还有很多很多的选项
shells are highly, highly configurable, and
shell 的可配置性非常强
it's not only shells that are configured
through these files,
不只是 shell 可以用文件配置
there are many other programs. As we saw for
example in the editors lecture, Vim is also
许多其他的程序也是如此
就像编辑器一课中的 vim
configured this way. We gave you this vimrc
file and told you to put it under your
vim 也是这样配置的
只要提供一个 vimrc 文件并且放在
home/.vimrc
~/.vimrc 中
and this is the same concept, but just
for Vim. It's just giving it a set of
同样的道理 但这是对 vim 有效
instructions that it should load when it's started,
so you can keep a configuration that you want.
它提供了 vim 启动时应当加载的指令
所以你可以保存一份自己想要的配置
And even non...
甚至连...
kind of a lot of programs will support this. For instance,
my terminal emulator, which is another concept,
很多的程序都支持这一类配置
比如 我的终端模拟器 当然这又是另一样玩意
which is the program that is
也就是运行 shell
running the shell, in a way, and displaying
this into the screen in my computer.
并且将 shell 显示在电脑屏幕上的程序
It can also be configured this way, so
也可以通过这种方式配置
if I modify this I can
如果我修改配置
change the size of the font. Like right now, for
example, I have increased the font size a lot
我就可以修改字体的大小
比如 我现在就把字体调大了很多
for demonstration purposes, but
这仅仅是演示一下
if I change this entry and make it for example
但如果我修改这一行 然后调成...比如说
28 and write this value, you see that
the size of the font has changed,
28 然后保存
你可以看到字体的大小改变了
because I edited this text file that specifies
how my terminal emulator should work.
因为我修改了终端模拟器的配置文件
Any questions so far?
有疑问吗
With dotfiles.
关于点文件
Okay, it can be a bit daunting knowing that there
is like this endless wall of configurations,
没关系 面对浩如烟海的配置
and how do you go about learning
about what can be configured?
还要学习配置它们的方法
肯定会有点害怕
The good news is that
好消息是
we have linked you to really good
resources in the lecture notes.
我们在课堂笔记中提供了很棒的资源
But the main idea is that a lot of people really like
just configuring these tools and have uploaded
主要是有很多人喜欢折腾这些工具的配置
their configuration files to GitHub, another
different kind of repositories online.
还把他们的配置传到 GitHub 上
这是另一种在线代码仓库
So for example, here we are on GitHub,
比如说 我们在 GitHub
we search for dotfiles, and
can see that there are like
搜索 dotfiles 就会有结果显示出来
thousands of repositories of people sharing
their configuration files. We have also...
数以千计的代码仓库 都是其他人分享的配置
Like, the class instructors
have linked our dotfiles.
比如 这门课程的导师就提供了我们的 dotfile
So if you really want to know how
any part of our setup is working
所以你如果很想知道我们设置中的任何部分是如何工作的
you can go through it and try to figure it out.
你可以自己去翻看 尝试想明白
You can also feel free to ask us.
你也可以随时来问我们
If we go for example to this repository here
我们看看这个仓库
we can see that there's many, many
files that you can configure.
可以看到有很多文件可供配置
For example, there is one for bash, the first couple of ones
are for git, that will be probably be covered in the
比如 这里有个 bashrc
最前面的几个是 git 的配置
大概在下堂课
version control lecture tomorrow.
讲版本控制系统的时候提到
If we go for example to the bash profile, which is
a different form of what we saw in the bashrc,
我们看看这个 .bash_profile
它的形式不同于 bashrc
it can be really useful because
you can learn through
它很有用 因为你只要
just looking at the manual page, but the
manual pages is, a lot of the time
看看手册就能学会
但是手册对选项的解释 只是大篇幅地
just kind of like a descriptive explanation
of all the different options
把所有选项本身描述了一遍
and sometimes it's more helpful
有时 更有用的反而是
going through examples of what people have done
and trying to understand why they did it
阅读其他人已经写好的示例
并且尝试理解他们这样写的原因
and how it's helping their workflow.
以及这对他们工作流有何帮助
We can say here that this person has
done case-insensitive globbing.
可以发现 这个人设置了大小无关的通配符
We covered globbing as this
kind of filename expansion
这在脚本和工具中是一种通配符技巧
trick in the shell scripting and tools.
可以用来匹配文件名
And here you say no, I don't want this to matter,
看到这你可能会说 我不希望
whether using uppercase and lowercase,
大小写会影响通配符
and just setting this option in the shell
for these things to work this way
那只要这样设置 shell 就可以让它们这样工作
Similarly, there is for example aliases.
类似地 也有关于别名的示例
Here you can see a lot of aliases that this
person is doing. For example, "d" for
你可以看到这人设置了很多别名
"d" for "Dropbox", sorry, because
that's just much shorter.
比如 d 代表 Dropbox
抱歉 但这真的短多了
"g" for "git"...
g 代表 git
Say we go, for example, with vimrc. It
can be actually very, very informative,
这些文件的信息量会很大
比如 vimrc
going through this and trying
to extract useful information.
可以从中提炼出有用的信息
We do not recommend just kind of getting one huge blob
of this and copying this into your config files,
我们不推荐把这些例子大段大段地复制粘贴到你自己的配置里
because maybe things are prettier, but you might
not really understand what is going on.
因为虽然效果会很好
但你可能无法真正理解它们的作用
Lastly one thing I want to mention
about dotfiles is that
关于点文件我最后想说说
people not only try to push these
人们把这些配置传上去
files into GitHub just so other
people can read it, that's
不只是为了让别人看到
one reason. They also make really sure they can
还以此确保能够复现自己的设置
reproduce their setup. And to do that
they use a slew of different tools.
为了做到这件事 他们会用很多不同的工具
Oops, went a little too far.
哦 扯得有点远了
So GNU Stow is, for example, one of them
比如说 GNU Stow 就是一种
and the trick that they are doing is
他们还用了一个技巧
they are kind of putting all their
dotfiles in a folder and they are
把点文件都放在同一个文件夹中
faking to the system, using
a tool called symlinks,
然后用软链接来欺骗系统
that they are actually what
they're not. I'm gonna
让系统认为默认路径中有文件
draw really quick what I mean by that.
我来画个图解释一下
So a common folder structure might look
like you have your home folder and
通常的文件夹结构长这样
in this home folder you might have your
在家目录里 你可能会有
bashrc, that contains your bash configuration,
you might have your vimrc and
bash 的配置文件 bashrc
也可能有 vimrc
it would be really great if you could
keep this under version control.
如果能用版本管理系统去管理它们就好了
But the thing is, you might not
want to have a git repository,
但问题是 你不会想在家目录下开 git 仓库
which will be covered tomorrow,
我们明天会提到这个
in your home folder.
So what people usually do is they
create a dotfiles repository,
所以人们通常单独建一个仓库
and then they have entries here for their
用来存放配置文件
bashrc and their vimrc. And
this is where actually
比如 bashrc 和 vimrc
这才是这些文件
the files are
实际所在的位置
and what they are doing is they're just
然后他们要做的就是
telling the OS to forward, whenever anyone
告诉 OS 转发所有
wants to read this file or write to this file,
just forward this to this other file.
想要读写这个文件的请求到这个实际的文件
This is a concept called symlinks
这一概念称作软链接
and it's useful in this scenario,
在这种情形下 十分实用
but it in general it's a really
useful tool in UNIX
但总的来说 它在 UNIX 中是个十分好用的工具
that we haven't covered so far in the lectures
我们这堂课讲不了那么多
but you might be...
但是你可能
that you should be familiar with.
应当很熟悉这个工具
And in general, the syntax will be "ln -s"
总的来说 它的写法是用 ln -s
for specifying a symbolic link and then
you will put the path to the file
来指定一个符号链接 然后是一个路径
that you want to create and then the
你的文件实际所在的位置
symlink that you want to create.
接着是你要创建的软链接的位置
And
并且
All these all these kind of fancy tools
that we're seeing here listed,
这里列出了刚才的所有炫酷工具
they all amount to doing some sort of this trick, so
that you can have all your dotfiles neat and tidy
它们都可以用于这一技巧
这样你就可以使自己的点文件干净整齐
into a folder, and then they can be
version-controlled, and they can be
放在同一个文件夹中 带有版本控制
symlinked so the rest of the programs can
find them in their default locations.
还能用软链接让其他程序在默认位置找到它们
Any questions regarding dotfiles?
对点文件有任何疑问吗
Do you need to have the dotfiles in your home folder,
and then also dotfiles in the version control folder?
需要在家目录保留点文件的同时 在另一个仓库文件夹里存放一样的点文件吗
So what you will have is,
pretty much every program,
情况是这样的
几乎所有的程序
for example bash,
比如说 bash
will always look for "home/.bashrc".
bash 会始终寻找 ~/.bashrc
That's where the program is going to look for.
这是它会寻找的文件
What you do when you do a symlink
is, you place your "home/.bashrc"
你在添加软链接的时候 是在 ~/.bashrc 这个位置
it's just a file that is kind
of a special file in UNIX,
它是 UNIX 的一种特殊文件
that says oh, whenever you want to read
this file go to this other file.
它会告诉系统 你要读这个文件的时候 得去找另一个某某文件
There's no content, like there is no...
它本身没有内容 就像
your aliases are not part of this dotfile. That file
is just kind of like a pointer, saying now you should
你的别名一样 软链接不是文件本身的一部分
软链接文件就像是指针 告诉你应该
go that other way.
去找另一条路
And by doing that you can have your other file
这样一来 你就可以让其他文件
in that other folder.
也可以在这里读写
If version controlling is not useful, think about
如果版本控制不大好理解
what if you want to have them in your Dropbox
folder, so they're synced to the cloud,
你就想想 如果你想把它们同步到 Dropbox 文件夹
这样就把它们同步到云端了
for example. That's kind of another use case
where like symlinks could be really useful
这也是软链接的一个使用情形
So you don't need the folder dotfiles
to be in the home directory, right?
这样你就不用真的在家目录存放点文件了 对吧
Because you can just use the symlink,
that points somewhere else.
因为你可以只用软链接指到其他地方
As long as you have a way for the default path
to resolve wherever you have it, yeah.
只要你有办法让默认目录解析到实际的目录就行
Last thing I want to cover in the lecture...
这堂课的最后，我想说一说...
Oh, sorry, any other questions about dotfiles?
哦 抱歉 还有关于 dotfile 的问题吗
Last thing I want to cover in the lecture
is working with remote machines,
这堂课最后一个内容 是使用远程机器
which is a thing that you will run into,
这种情况 你迟早会遇上的
sooner or later.
And there are a few things that will make your life
much easier when dealing with remote machines
并且有些小玩意可以让你更容易使用远程机器
if you know about them.
只要你了解它们
Right now maybe because you are
using the Athena cluster,
现在你可能在用 Athena 集群
but later on, during your programming career,
但是以后 在你的编程生涯中
it's pretty sure that
可以确信
there is a fairly ubiquitous
concept of having your
一种相当普遍的观念是
local working environment and then having some
production server that is actually running the
你有自己本地的工作环境
但代码实际上在服务器的生产环境中运行
code, so it is really good to get familiar
所以熟悉如何应付远程服务器
about how to work in/with remote machines.
是很好的一件事
So the main command for working
with remote machines is SSH.
使用远程服务器的主要指令是 ssh
SSH is just like a secure shell, it's
just gonna take the responsibility for
ssh 就是一种安全的 shell
它负责
reaching wherever we want or tell it to go
连到我们要它连接的地方
and trying to open a session there.
然后尝试在上面开一个会话
So here the syntax is:
它的用法如下
"JJGO" is the user that I want
to use in the remote machine,
“JJGO” 是我要在远程服务器上使用的用户名
and this is because the user is
这是因为这个用户名
different from the one I have my local machine,
which will be the case a lot of the time,
和我本地的用户名不一样
很多时候都是如此
then the "@" is telling the
terminal that this separates
然后 这个 @ 告诉终端
what the user is from what the address is.
在何处分开用户名和主机名
And here I'm using an IP address because
what I'm actually doing is
这里我用了一个 IP 地址
因为我实际上
I have a virtual machine in my computer,
有一台虚拟机在我的电脑里
that is the one that is remote right now.
这台虚拟机就是我要连接的远程机器
And I'm gonna be SSH'ing into it. This is the
我要用 ssh 连过去
URL that I'm using,
这就是我用的 URL
sorry, the IP that I'm using,
抱歉 是指我用的 IP
but you might also see things like
但你还会看到一些比如
oh I want to SSH as "JJGO"
哦 我想以 JJGO 的身份
at "foobar.mit.edu"
连到 "foobar.mit.edu"
That's probably something more
common, if you are using some
这会是更为常见的情况
remote server that has a DNS name.
你的远程机器可能有个域名
So going back to a regular command,
回到正常的指令
we try to SSH, it asks us for a password,
我们尝试 ssh 连接
它现在要求我们提供密码
really common thing.
再正常不过了
And now we're there. We have...
好 登上了
we're still in our same terminal emulator
我们仍然在自己的终端模拟器里
but right now SSH is kind of forwarding the
entire virtual display to display what the
但现在 ssh 把整个虚拟显示器转发了过来
remote shell is displaying. And
we can execute commands here and
这就是远程机器上 shell 的内容
我们执行指令
we'll see the remote files
远程机器上的文件就显示出来了
A couple of handy things to know about
SSH, that were briefly covered in the
还有些很顺手的 ssh 技巧
data wrangling lecture, is that
SSH is not only good for just
曾在数据整理一课中简要提到过
ssh 不止很适合连接
opening connections. It will also let
you just execute commands remotely.
它还可以让你远程执行指令
So for example, if I do that, it's gonna ask me
比如说 如果我这样做 终端就会再次询问我的密码
what is my password?, again.
And it's executing this command
然后它就会执行代码
then coming back to my terminal
再回到我的终端
and piping the output of what that
command was, in the remote machine,
输出远程机器的输出
through the standard output in my current shell.
到我这个 shell 的标准用户输出里
And I could have this in...
我还可以把这个...
I could have this in a pipe, and
我还可以把这个灌进管道
this will work and we'll just
这是行得通的
drop all this output and then have a local pipe
我们可以把远端的输出放进本地的管道
where I can keep working.
这样我就可以在本地继续工作
So far, it has been kind of inconvenient,
having to type our password.
到现在为止 有点麻烦的是要输入密码
There's one really good trick for this.
有个很妙的技巧来对付这个
It's we can use something called "SSH keys".
我们如果用一种叫做 "SSH 密钥" 的东西
SSH keys just use public key encryption
SSH 密钥使用了非对称加密
to create a pair of SSH keys, a public
key and a private key, and then
来产生一对 SSH 密钥
一个公钥和一个私钥
you can give the server the
public part of the key.
然后你可以把公钥存到远程服务器上
So you copy the public key and
then whenever you try to
把公钥复制过去以后
authenticate instead of using your password,
it's gonna use the private key to
然后你不想用密码的时候
你的机器就会用私钥
prove to the server that you are
actually who you say you are.
向服务器证明你确实是你宣称的身份
We can quickly showcase how you will go
这里快速演示一下你要如何使用
about doing this.
这一种认证方式
Right now I don't have any SSH keys,
so I'm gonna create a couple of them.
现在我没有 SSH 密钥
所以我要生成一对
First thing, it's just gonna ask
me where I want this key to live.
首先
程序会询问存放密钥的位置
Unsurprisingly, it's doing this.
它这样做很符合预期
This is my home folder and then
it's using this ".ssh" path,
这是我的家目录
它会使用其中的 .ssh 文件夹
which refers back to the same concept
that we covered earlier about having
这与我们刚刚提到的点文件的概念是一致的
dotfiles. Like ".ssh" is a folder
that contains a lot of the
.ssh 是一个存放着许多
configuration files for how
you want SSH to behave.
配置文件的文件夹
这些文件控制 SSH 的行为
So it will ask us a passphrase.
接着 我们要提供一个密码
The passphrase is to encrypt
the private part of the key
这个密码是用来加密私钥的
because if someone gets your private key,
if you don't have a password protected
当你的私钥落入他人手中
如果你的私钥没有密码的保护
private key, if they get that key
得到私钥的人
they can use that key to impersonate
you in any server.
就可以用你的私钥冒充你的身份
Whereas if you add a passphrase,
而当你添加了密码以后
they will have to know what the passphrase
is to actually use the key.
他们在使用私钥之前会被要求提供密码
It has created a keypair. We can check that
these two files are now under ssh.
密钥对已经创建好了
我们可以在 .ssh 文件夹里查看它们
And we can see...
我们还可以看到
We have these two files: we have
the 25519 and the public key.
我们有两个文件
我们有这个 25519 和一个公钥文件
And if we "cat" through the output,
如果我们 cat 一下这两个文件
that key is actually not like
any fancy binary file, it's
就会发现它们不是二进制的
just a text file that has the contents
of the public key and some
而是写着公钥本体的文本
alias name for it, so we can
know what this public key is.
还有它的别名
这样我们就能知道这个公钥的归属
The way we can tell the server that
we're authorized to SSH there
这样就能告诉服务器
我们有权限用 ssh 连过去
is by just actually copying this file,
like copying this string into a file,
只要把公钥复制到
比如复制进一个文件
that is ".ssh/authorized_keys".
也就是 .ssh/authorized_keys
So here what I'm doing is I'm
接下来我要做的是
catting the output of this file
把 cat 输出的文件内容
which is just this line of
text that we want to copy
也就是我们想要拷贝的这一行公钥
and I'm piping that into SSH and then remotely
用管道灌进 ssh
送到服务器上
I'm asking "tee" to dump the contents
of the standard input
我执行了 tee 来获取标准用户输入的内容
into ".ssh/authorized_keys".
转存到 .ssh/authorized_keys 里
And if we do that, obviously it's
gonna ask us for a password.
如果我们那样做
ssh 显然会要我们提供密码
It was copied, and now we
can check that if we try
复制完了
现在我们可以试着再连一次 ssh 来验证
to SSH again,
It's going to first ask us for a passphrase
我们需要提供私钥的密码
but you can arrange that so that
it's saved in the session
但你可以配置有效时间
这样它就能在整个会话期间被缓存
and we didn't actually have to
type the key for the server.
这样就不用输入服务器的密码了
And I can kind of show that again.
我可以再演示一次
More things that are useful.
还有更多有用的小玩具
Oh, we can do...
哦 我们可以
If that command seemed a little bit janky,
如果刚才的指令看起来有点灵
you can actually use this command
that is built for this,
你可以用这个指令
他是专为传送公钥准备的
so you don't have to kind of
craft this "ssh t" command.
这样你就不用自己写 ssh tee 的指令了
That is just called "ssh-copy-id".
这个指令写作 ssh-copy-id
And we can do the same
我们一样可以试一下
and it's gonna copy the key.
然后它就会发送我的公钥
And now, if we try to SSH,
随后我们尝试 ssh 连接
we can SSH without actually
typing any key at all,
就可以直接登录 不用给私钥输密码
or any password.
也不用输入服务器的密码了
More things.
再说一点
We will probably want to copy files.
我们可能会想在机器之间拷贝一些文件
You cannot use "CP"
这时候没法用 cp
but you can use "SCP", for "SSH copy".
但是可以用 scp 也就是 ssh copy
And here we can specify that we want
to copy this local file called notes
这里 我们可以指定要拷贝的本地文件的名字
比如这个 notes
and the syntax is kind of similar.
它的用法和 cp 很像
We want to copy to this remote and
我们想把它拷贝到远程机器上
then we have a semicolon to separate
what the path is going to be.
然后我们用冒号把主机名和目标路径隔开
And then we have
然后我们
oh, we want to copy this as notes
哦 我们想让它依然叫做 notes
but we could also copy this as foobar.
但我们也可以换个文件名 比如 foobar
And if we do that, it has been executed
我们执行一下这个指令
一下就跑完了 很快啊
and it's telling us that all the
contents have been copied there.
它还会告诉我们所有的内容已经复制过去了
If you're gonna be copying a lot of files,
如果你要复制很多文件
there is a better command
that you should be using
那你该用一个更好的指令
that is called "RSYNC". For example, here
叫做 rsync
比如说
just by specifying these three flags,
只要指定这三个参数
I'm telling RSYNC to kind of preserve
all the permissions whenever possible
就能让 rsync 尽可能保留这些文件的访问权限
to try to check if the file
has already been copied.
并且检查文件是否已经被复制过
For example, SCP will try to copy
files that are already there.
而 scp 会尝试复制已经存在的目标文件
This will happen for example
if you are trying to copy
这种情况会发生在你的复制过程中途
and the connection interrupts
in the middle of it.
连接突然断开的时候
SCP will start from the very beginning,
trying to copy every file,
scp 会从起始处重新复制
尝试复制每一个文件
whereas RSYNC will continue
from where it stopped.
而 rsync 会从进度中断处继续
And here,
接下来
we ask it to copy the entire folder and
我们要求它复制整个文件夹
it's just really quickly
copied the entire folder.
它很快就能完整复制
One of the other things to know about SSH is that
关于 ssh 还有一个要知道的
the equivalent of the dot file
for SSH is the "SSH config".
就是 ssh 的配置文件在 ~/.ssh/config
So if we edit the SSH config to be
所以如果我们修改它
If I edit the SSH config to
look something like this,
比方说我把它改成这个样子
instead of having to, every
time, type "ssh jjgo",
与其每次都要键入 ssh jjgo
having this really long string so I can
like refer to this specific remote,
用那么长的一串来代表我要连接的机器
I want to refer, with the specific user name,
还有我的用户名
I can have something here that says
我不如直接在这写好
this is the username, this
is the host name, that this
这是用户名
这是主机名
host is referring to and you should
use this identity file.
还有应当使用的鉴权密钥
And if I copy this,
我要把这个复制过去
this is right now in my local folder,
它现在在这个目录下面
I can copy this into ssh.
我可以把它复制到 .ssh
Now, instead of having to do this really
long command, I can just say
现在我就不用敲那么长的指令了
我可以直接写
I just want to SSH into the host called VM.
我想要连接到这个叫 vm 的主机
And by doing that, it's grabbing all that
configuration from the SSH config
这样 它就会从 .ssh/config 读取所有的配置
and applying it here.
然后在这里使用
This solution is much better than something
like creating an alias for SSH,
这就像是给 ssh 创建别名一样
because other programs like SCP and RSYNC
而其他程序 比如 scp 和 rsync
also know about the dotfiles for SSH and
will use them whenever they are there.
它们也会用 ssh 的 dotfile
也会在被调用的时候读取它
Last thing I want to cover about remote machines is
that here, for example, we'll have tmux and we can,
关于远程机器 我最后要讲的一个东西是
我们可以用 tmux 之类的软件
like I was saying before, we
can start editing some file
就像我之前说的
可以在里面编辑文件
and we can start running some job.
还可以在里面运行一些任务
For example, something like HTOP.
比如说 htop 什么的
And this is running here, we can
它在正常运作的时候
detach from it,
我们可以暂时离开它
close the connection and
关掉连接以后
then SSH back. And then, if you do "tmux a",
再连回去
执行一下 tmux a
everything is as you left it, like
nothing has really changed.
所有的东西都还在
就好像什么都发生一样
And if you have things executing there in
the background, they will keep executing.
如果你把它们留在后台
那它们就会一直运行
I think that, pretty much, ends
all I have to say for this tool.
我觉得 关于这个工具 说这么多应该够了
Any questions related to remote machines?
还有关于远程机器的问题吗
That's a really good question.
So what I do for that,
好问题
我实际上做的是
Oh, yes, sorry.
哦 是 抱歉
So the question is, how do you deal with
trying to use tmux in your local machine,
所以 问题是
要如何在自己的机器上使用 tmux 的同时
and also trying to use tmux
in the remote machine?
也在远程机器上使用 tmux
There are a couple of tricks
for dealing with that.
有很多技巧处理这个问题
The first one is changing the prefix.
其一是修改快捷键
So what I do, for example, is
我要做的是
in my local machine the prefix I have
changed from "Ctrl+B" to "Ctrl+A" and
在我的本地机器上把脱离的快捷键从 Ctrl+B 改成 Ctrl+A
then in remove machines this is still "Ctrl+B".
然后脱离远程机器的 tmux 时仍然使用 Ctrl+B
So I can kind of swap between,
这样我就可以自由切换了
if I want to do things to the
local tmux I will do "Ctrl+A"
如果想在本地做事 就按 Ctrl+A
and if I want to do things to the
remote tmux I would do "Ctrl+B".
如果想在远程机器上做事 就按 Ctrl+B
Another thing is that you
can have separate configs,
此外 你还可以给它们指定不同的配置
so I can do something like this, and then...
然后就能做一些...
Ah, because I don't have my own ssh config, yeah.
啊 我好像没有自己的 .ssh/config
But if you...
但如果你
Um, I can SSH "VM".
恩 我可以连到 vm 上
Here, what you see,
看这里
the difference between these
two bars, for example,
这两个状态栏就是不一样的
is because the tmux config is different.
因为它们的配置不同
As you will see in the exercises,
the tmux configuration is in
在练习题里你会看到
tmux 的配置文件在
the tmux.conf
~/.tmux.conf
And in tmux.conf,
而在 .tmux.conf 中
here you can do a lot of things like changing
the color depending on the host you are
你可以做很多事情
比如根据所在的主机改变状态栏的颜色
so you can get like quick visual
feedback about where you are, or
这样你就可以很快得到视觉反馈
知道你在哪台机器上
if you have a nested session. Also, tmux will,
在你堆叠了很多 tmux 的时候很好用
此外
if you're in the same host and you
try to tmux within a tmux session,
在你尝试在同一台机器上套娃 tmux 的时候
it will kind of prevent you from doing
it so you don't run into issues.
它会阻止你这样做 以避免出现问题
Any other questions related, to kind
of all the topics we have covered.
对于我们刚才提到的所有东西 还有任何疑问吗
Another answer to that question is
also, if you type the prefix twice,
这问题还有另一个解法
如果你连续两次按快捷键
it sends it once to the underlying shell.
它会先给底下的 shell 发送
So the local binding is "Ctrl+A" and
the remote binding is "Ctrl+A",
比如 如果本地和远端都绑定了 Ctrl+A 快捷键
You could type "Ctrl+A", "Ctrl+A" and then "D", for
example, detaches from the remote, basically.
可以按两次 Ctrl+A 后按 D
就可以只脱离远程机器的 tmux
I think that ends the class for today, there's a bunch
of exercises related to all these main topics and
我觉得今天的课就到这里了
我们安排了一些练习 它们与刚才提到的几个话题相关
we're gonna be holding office hours today, too.
So feel free to come and ask us any questions.
我们今天也会在办公室值班答疑
你可以随时来问我们任何问题